Finding Aid for Mark L. Ireland papers, 1925-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mark L. Ireland papers 1925-1962
Ireland, Mark Lorin.
1 linear foot
85230 Aa 2
Washington, D. C. and Chesaning, Michigan, resident. Correspondence, research files, and photographs, largely relating to the writing of a centennial history of Chesaning, Saginaw County, Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Mary Rogers (donor no. 5690 ) and came to the library in 1980.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Mark Lorin Ireland (b. 1880) wrote a history of Chesaning, Michigan.
The Mark Ireland collection includes correspondence, genealogical information collected on settlers to Chesaning, and research notes on his history Place of the Big Rock: Chesaning, Michigan, 1842-1950.
Subjects:
Chesaning (Mich.).; Saginaw County (Mich.).
- Correspondence, 1925-1962
  - Undated, 1891, 1925-1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952-1962 (Box 1)
- Research for Book
  - Early history, 'How They Came...' (Chap. III, V) (Box 1)
  - Pioneer Life (Chap. VII)
    - Notes and materials (Box 1)
    - 'The Pioneer Tradition' (Box 1)
    - 'As We Were--Family Life in America, 1850-1900' (Box 1)
    - Sports and entertainment, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Child Life, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Development of Local Self-government (Chap. VIII) (Box 1)
  - Mail Service (Chap. X) (Box 1)
  - Trails, Roads and Highways (Chap. XI), 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Home story (Chap. XII) (Box 1)
  - Food (Chap. XII), 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Clothing (Chap. XIV), 9 folders (Box 1)
  - Railroad (Chap. XV) (Box 1)
  - Agriculture (Chap. XVII) (Box 1)
  - Medical Service and Public Health (Chap. XVIII), 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspapers (Box 1)
  - Early Schools (Chap. XX) (Box 1)
  - Organizations (Chap. XXI) (Box 1)
  - Riot at Chesaning (Chap. XXII) (Box 1)
  - Holidays (Box 1)
  - War Years (Chap. XXV) (Box 1)
  - Churches (Chap. XXVI) (Box 1)
  - People and Places (Chap. XXVII), 4 folders (Box 1)
- Topical and other research material
  - Industry and manufacturing (Box 1)
  - Banking (Box 1)
  - Business (Box 1)
  - Land (Box 1)
  - "Firsts" in Chesaning (Box 1)
  - Footnotes and general references, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Personal file (Box 1)
  - Book-related materials: notes about working on Chesaning history (Box 1)
  - Methodology (Box 1)
  - Bibliography (Box 1)